Yo!
高校生活といえば薔薇色
"People remember their high school days as the high point of their lives."
"And people remember the high point of their lives as their high school days."
薔薇色といえば高校生活
そう言われるのが当たり前なくらい 高校生活はいつも薔薇色な扱いだよな
People say these things because everyone holds fond memories of their time in high school.
さりとて すべての高校生が薔薇色を望んでいるわけではないと俺は思うんだが
However, I doubt that every high school student would want to remember their school life that way.
たとえば勉学にもスポーツにも
For example, if neither studying,
nor sports,
nor socializing are of interest to someone, what then?
色恋沙汰にも興味を示さない人間というのもいるんじゃないのか
What if there are students who prefer to keep a low profile?
いわゆる灰色を好む生徒というのもいるんじゃないのか
Though, I guess that would be a pretty lonely way to live.
まあ それって随分さびしい生き方だとは思うがな
奉太郎に自虐趣味があったとは知らなかったね
I didn't know you liked making yourself suffer, Houtarou.
自虐趣味？
Making myself suffer?
勉強にもスポーツにも色恋沙汰にも後ろ向き 常に灰色の人間
You turn your back on studying, sports and socializing.
A real low-profile kind of guy.
それって奉太郎のことだろ
You were talking about yourself before, right?
I wouldn't say I'm turning my back on them.
別に後ろ向きなわけじゃない
奉太郎的にはね
Of course you wouldn't.
「省エネ」なんだよね 奉太郎は
You're just saving energy, right?
You can't be bothered doing anything that isn't worth your while.
ただ単に面倒で浪費としか思えないことにゃ興味が持てない
そのモットーは即ち
Your motto is none other than...
やらなくてもいいことならやらない
"I don't do anything I don't have to.
やらなければいけないことなら手短に
What I have to do, I do quickly."
Yep.
だね
でもね 奉太郎
But you know,
この多彩の部活動の伝統神山高校で部活にも入ってない奉太郎は
in a school with as many clubs as this one,
someone like you who doesn't join a single one is the epitome of keeping a low profile.
結果だけ見れば灰色そのものってことだよ
その奉太郎がさびしい生き方だなんて 自虐趣味以外の何物でもない
If you say that's a lonely way to live,
then clearly you must want yourself to suffer.
口の減らない奴だなあ
You just can't shut up, can you?
Isn't it a bit late for that? We've been hanging around each other since junior high.
何を今更 中学からの付き合いだろ
まあいい 先に帰れ
Anyway, you can head off without me.
先に？ どういうこと？
What do you mean?
それは！ まさかそんな！
No way!
Don't tell me you...
Club entry
Club name
Club
Classics
A club application form?
入部届け？ 奉太郎が部活に！
You're joining a club?
しかも古典部！
And the Classics Club, at that?
You've heard of it?
知ってるか
もちろんさ だけどなんだって奉太郎が古典？
Of course I have!
But why would you choose the Classics Club?
これは 奉太郎のお姉さんからの手紙だねえ
Is that a letter from your sister?
インドから送ってきた ベナレスだかどこかだか
It just arrived from India.
From Benares, or whatever that place is called.
Let's see.
どれ
これは困ったねえ お姉さんの頼みか
Oh, poor you. So your sister put you up to it.
部員がいなくて廃部寸前らしい 存続のために入部しろだとさ
They don't have enough members, so the club's at risk of being disbanded.
She wants me to join to keep the club alive.
Doesn't your sister know all kinds of things...
お姉さんの特技は確か
合気道と逮捕術 痛くしようと思えばかなり痛い
...about aikido holds, yeah.
She would make it very painful to refuse.
これは断れない
Yeah, you can't say no to that!
まあ 特にやりたいことがないのは姉貴が書いた通りなんだが
She even says here that there's nothing much to do in the club.
部員がいないんだよね
Well, there's nobody there, right?
Yeah.
ああ
だったら古典部の部室は一人占めじゃないか
Then you could have the clubroom all to yourself!
学校の中にプライベートスペースが持てるってのも結構いいものだよ
It'd be pretty cool having your own private corner of the school, right?
プライベートスペース
A private corner, huh?
神校 FIGHT  FIGHT  FIGHT
Kami High! Fight-o! Fight-o!
エネルギー消費の大きい生き方に敬礼
To those living high-energy lives, I salute you.
Staff Room
よく勘違いされるのだが 俺は特に省エネが優れていると思っているわけではない
Contrary to popular belief,
I don't consider saving energy to be objectively the best approach.
I'm not looking down on energetic people.
活力ある連中を小馬鹿になどにしてはいないのだ
自分のモットーに忠実なだけ
I just stick to my motto:
やらなくてもいいことならやらない
"I don't do anything I don't have to.
やらなければいけないことなら手短にだ
What I have to do, I do quickly."
Oreki
Look, look!
ほら これ
もう
Earth Sci. Prep. room
The fourth floor of the auxiliary building.
特別棟の四階 最果てだな
It's the end of the world.
退屈な窓辺に吹き込む風に
Bored, sitting on the windowsill,
顔を顰めたのは照れくさ　その裏返し
I frown at the wind to hide my awkwardness
Hyouka
KamiGami
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
曖昧に頷く掌の今日
I nod uncertainly as I shape
the future in my hands feeling mighty
描いてる自分は少し大袈裟で
I feel that the wind is bringing change
何かが変わりそうな気がしているよ
心に呼びかける君のせいだね
I guess that's your fault for calling out to my heart
曇り空覗いた予感
The cloudy sky tells a tale of what's to come
手を伸ばそう　いつよりも力強い勇気で
Spread our wings with more courage than ever before
光も影もまだ遠くで
Light and dark are still vague in the distance
それでも僕らは優しさの理由が知りたい
but still we want to know the reason behind kindness
今は誰の名前でもない
No one so far has ever reached
輝きの彼方へ
the shining distance far beyond
全部過去になる前に見つけに行こう
Let's get there before the past takes it all
Good afternoon!
こんにちは
The esteemed Classics Club has been restored
传统的古籍研究社之复活
あなたって 古典部だったんですか 折木さん
You're in the Classics Club, right, Oreki?
Who're you?
誰だ？
You forgot?
わかりませんか？ 千反田です 千反田えるです
I'm Chitanda.
Chitanda Eru.
Sorry, doesn't ring a bell.
すまん 全然わからないんだが
折木奉太郎さんですよね 一年B組の
You're Oreki Houtarou from 1-B, right?
Yeah.
I'm in 1-A.
私一年A組なんです
That doesn't really...
あのな それじゃあ説明になってなっ
1-A? Could it have been for electives?
A組？ 選択科目か
Did we take Music together?
もしかして 音楽の授業で一緒だったか
Yep.
はい
We only had one class together so far!
まだ一回しかやってない授業だぞ どんな記憶力だ
She has one hell of a memory.
あ それで千反田さん なぜこの部屋に？
And what are you doing here, Chitanda?
はい
Oh, right.
I joined the Classics Club,
私古典部に入ったので ご挨拶に伺ったんです
so I thought I'd say hi.
私古典部に入ったので
I joined the Classics Club...
古典部に？ なんでまた
You joined the club...
Why?
It was due to... personal reasons.
一身上の都合がありまして 折木さんは？
How about you, Oreki?
いや 部員がいるなら大いに結構
Well, if there's already someone in the club, it doesn't matter.
姉貴 喜べ 古典部はめでたく存続したぞ
Rejoice, Sis.
The club lives on.
じゃ 俺はこれで
Well then, I'm off.
You're going home?
もうお帰りですか
ああ 頑張れよ あと戸締りも頼む
Yeah. Have fun.
And don't forget to lock up afterward.
I can't lock up afterward!
私戸締りできません
なんで？
Why?
鍵を持ってませんから
I don't have the key.
Here.
はい
どうして折木さんがそれを持ってるんですか
Why do you have that?
What do you mean?
どうしてって 鍵がなければロックされた教室には入れないだろう
Without the key, how could I have unlocked the door?
そういや お前 あ 失礼
That reminds me, how the hell...
'Scuse me.
How did you get in here?
千反田さんはなんでこの部屋に入れたんだ？
The door wasn't locked.
鍵がかかってなかったからです
俺が来たときは閉まってたけど
It was when I got here...
You mean the door was locked?
閉まってたって そのドアがですか？
そうだが
Yeah, I gu—
ということは 私は閉じ込められていたってことですね
That means I was locked in here!
You locked it from the inside, didn't you?
お前が鍵をかけたんだろう？ 内側から
そんなことはしていません
I didn't do anything like that!
だが鍵は俺が持ってる お前以外に誰がロックできるんだ
But I had the key! Who else could have locked it?
By the way, you haven't introduced me to your friend.
ところで そちらはお友達ですか
里志
Satoshi.
Sorry, sorry. I didn't mean to eavesdrop.
いやあ ごめんごめん 盗み聞きのつもりはなかったんだけど
つもりじゃないだろ
That's reassuring.
そうは言ってもさ 木石のごとき奉太郎が夕暮れ迫る教室の窓際で
It was just that, from the ground I caught the miraculous sight of
Houtarou talking with a girl in an empty classroom lit by the setting sun,
女の子と二人ってのが下から見えちゃったら
気になるのが当然ってもんだよ
and I couldn't help but be intrigued!
I didn't want to intrude on your tryst, but I didn't know—
放課後の逢瀬を邪魔する気はなかったし
出歯亀なんて未経験で
あの あの 私
Um, I...
本気で言ってるのか
Are you serious?
まさか ジョークだよ
Of course not. Just kidding.
そうですか
Thank God.
すまんな こいつはこういうやつなんだ
Sorry about that. He's always like this.
「ジョークは即興に限る 禍根を残せば嘘になる」ってね
"Jokes must be improvised, or they're just common lies."
これ僕のモットー
That's my motto.
Oreki, who's he?
折木さん こちらは？
He's Fukube Satoshi.
こいつは福部里志 似非粋人だ
A would-be man of the world.
Would-be?
似非？
That was great! Nice introduction, Houtarou!
うまい ナイスな紹介だよ 奉太郎
Nice to meet you, um...
初めまして えっと
千反田えるです
I'm Chitanda Eru.
ち 千反田さん！
Chitanda? You mean you're the Chitanda?
千反田さんって あの千反田さんですか
どうかしたのか
What do you mean?
奉太郎 千反田家の名前を聞いたことがないのかい
Houtarou, have you never heard of the Chitandas?
There are quite a few old families in Kamiyama,
神山市に旧家名家は少なくないけど
桁上がりの四名家といえば その筋じゃ有名だよ
but the "exponential four" are really famous.
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
The Juumonji family of the Arekusu Shrine,
荒楠神社の十文字家 書肆百日紅家
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
the Sarusuberi family, who own the bookstore,
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
豪農千反田家 山持ちの万人橋家さ
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
the Chitanda family, who are wealthy farmers,
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
and the Manninbashi family, who own a mountain.
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
Juumonji
Sarusuberu
Chitanda
Manninbashi
数字が一桁ずつ上がっていくから 人呼んで桁上がりの四名家
The first character in each of their names is an exponent of ten,
so people call them the "exponential four" families.
Really?
本当か
I don't know if we're famous or not,
名家かどうかは知りませんが そういう言い方は初めて聞きました
but I've never heard anyone say that before.
You made it up, didn't you.
創ったな
I like suggesting things like that every now and then.
たまには提唱者になりたい時もあるさ
でも 本当に桁上がりですね
But they really were exponential!
感心するなよ つけ上がるから
Don't encourage him, or you'll never get rid of him.
しかもその千反田家の長女は成績優秀 眉目秀麗
Anyway, the Chitandas' eldest daughter is well known to be
a shining young beauty with top-notch grades.
深窓の佳人として知られているんだ
I remember seeing her name a bunch of times on the prefectural honor roll for junior high.
中学時代県内模試の成績優秀者で よく名前を見かけたよ
Oh, you're that good?
ほほ そんなに
It's no big deal. I just happen to have a knack for exams.
たまたまです 試験なんてただの要領ですし
I didn't mean to embarrass you.
これは失礼
ところで 話は聞かせてもらったよ 実に興味深いね
Anyway, I heard the story. It's quite intriguing.
何がだ？
What do you mean?
千反田さんがこの部屋に閉じ込められていたことさ
About how Chitanda ended up being locked inside the room.
Oh, right!
あ そうでした
Door Open
私が来たときこの部屋の鍵は開いていました
When I went inside, the door was unlocked.
But Oreki said that when he came by later,
でも 後から来た折木さんは鍵が閉まってたと言ってます
Door Closed
the door had been locked.
不思議です
It's weird!
Door Closed
Door Open
Is it now?
どこがだ… 自分で閉めたこと忘れたんだろう
Couldn't you have just forgotten that you locked it?
いや 神校のドアは中も外も鍵でしかロックできないようになっているんだ
Nope. The doors in Kami High can only be locked with a key, even from the inside.
She couldn't have locked it from the inside.
千反田さんが中から鍵をかけることは不可能ってことだよ
Oh my...
これは
Your collection of useless knowledge is impressive as ever.
相変わらず無駄に博識だな
Call it a database, please.
データベースと言ってほしいね
Eh, it must have just been locked by mistake somehow.
まあ 鍵のことは何かの間違いだろう 俺は帰るぞ
I'm gonna head home.
待ってください 折木さん
Wait, Oreki!
なんだ
What?
気になります 私 なぜ閉じ込められたんでしょう
I can't stop thinking about it. Why was I locked inside?
もし閉じ込められたのでなければ どうしてこの教室に入ることができたんでしょう
And if I wasn't, how could I have entered the room?
仮に何かの間違いだというなら 誰のどういう間違いでしょうか
If it was a mistake, who made it and how?
Please, just consider it for a moment, Oreki!
ぜひ 折木さんも考えてください
Oreki...
折木さん
私 気になります
I can't stop thinking about it!
ああ そうだな 面白い
I guess. Sounds interesting.
少し考えてみるか
Okay, let's mull over this for a minute.
ありがとうこぞいます
Thank you very much!
折木さん 心当たりがあるんですか
Do you have any ideas?
千反田さん ちょっと待ってあげて
Chitanda, wait a moment please.
I'm just a database, so I can't draw conclusions,
僕は単なるデータベースだから 結論を出せないけど
but Houtarou is different.
奉太郎は違う
一旦考え出せば それなりに当てにはなるよ
If he starts thinking, he'll reach a conclusion.
Cut it out.
やかましい
さて
Let's see.
この部屋に入ったのはいつだ？
When did you enter the room?
About three minutes before you.
折木さんが来る三分前だと思います
Did you notice anything?
他に何か気付いたことは？
そういえば さっきから足元で カタコト音がしてます
Now that you mention it,
the floor's been making this clattering sound for some time.
え 僕には聞こえないけど
I don't hear anything.
聞こえますよ ほら
I can! Just listen!
千反田さん 耳いいねえ
Your hearing's pretty good, Chitanda.
Have you figured something out?
なんかわかったの 奉太郎
I guess.
まあなあ ちょうど下の階で再現されてるだろう
I think the same thing's happening on the floor below us.
さて
はは あの作業の間に千反田さんは地学準備室に入って
I see.
So Chitanda entered the room while he was working,
運悪く鍵を閉められたってことだね
and was unlucky enough to get locked inside.
貸し出し用の鍵は俺が持ってる
I have the key that's available for student use.
There's also a master key,
あとはマスターキーだけだが これは生徒は使えない
but that's not available to students.
That's how you figured it was someone who works here...
だから公務員さんだった
でも よく気付きましたね
You're pretty sharp to have realized that!
It's no big deal.
別に
まあ 室内にいながら
But what I don't get is how you couldn't hear the door being locked.
どうして千反田さんがロックの音に気付かなかったのかってのだけは俺にもわからんがね
あ それでしたら
Oh, as for that...
あの建物を見ていたんです
I was looking at that building.
古いね
It looks old.
ええ
Yeah.
Does it?
そうなのか
ああ ずば抜けて
Yeah. Ages older than the others.
By the way, we're not quite finished with the formalities.
ところで 挨拶がまだでしたね
挨拶？
What formalities?
Well,
ええ これから古典部で一緒に活動していくんですから
we'll be the Classics Club from now on.
"We"?
一緒に？
福部さんはどうですか 古典部
What do you think about it, Fukube? Will you join?
いいね 今日は面白かったし
Sounds good! Today was pretty cool!
I'm already in the Handicraft Club and Student Council, though...
総務員と手芸部の掛け持ちになっちゃうけど
うん 入るよ
But that's no problem! I'm in!
奉太郎もね
You too, Houtarou.
入部届けももう書いてるんだし
You already filled out your application, after all.
そうなんですか
You have?
Well, I'd rather...
あ いや それはだな
Please.
はい
Thank you.
はい 確かに
これからよろしくお願いしますね
I'm looking forward to working with you.
こちらこそ 奉太郎もよろしく
Me too.
And Houtarou, as well.
Oh, right. We should decide who's going to be the club president.
そうだ 部長を決めないといけませんね
What do you think?
どうしましょう
That's right.
そうだね 奉太郎はその手のは全然向いてないんだよ
Houtarou's no good, that much I'm certain about.
Are you happy, Sis?
姉貴よ 満足か
Really?
（そうなんですか 折木さんがうってつけだと思ったんですけど）
The esteemed Classics Club has been restored.
He looked pretty determined before.
伝統ある古典部の復活
そしてさようなら 俺の安寧と省エネの日々
And with it end my quiet, energy-saving days.
You totally misjudged him then, Chitanda.
（千反田さん それは誤解だよ）
No, I shouldn't give up on them just yet.
いや まだ別れは言わない
The thing is that he's this eco-friendly, extreme energy-saving lazy kind of guy.
I don't want to give up that peace. I'll put all I have into living the low-energy lifestyle.
俺は安寧を諦めない
省エネのために全力を尽くそう
But he's a pretty sharp thinker, right?
（でも普通だし 頭脳明晰って感じですよね）
The problem is...
問題は
this girl.
このお嬢様だ
清明
万物发而清净明洁
问谁人可知 此芽乃何草
Radiance of Spring
When all of nature is aglow with the radiance of spring,
a single bud may blossom into countless flowers.
Hyouka
昨日の放課後のことだ
Yesterday, after classes,
一年生の女子が特別棟の四階に行った
a first-year girl went to the fourth floor of the auxiliary building.
その時音楽室から 月光の美しい旋律が聞こえてきた
月光：贝多芬乐曲
The Moonlight Sonata's delicate beauty reached her ears from the music room.
The setting sun bathed her in red light.
校舎を染める真赤な夕日 その麗しい音色は
Its beautiful tone—
異議あり
I object.
昨日は雨で夕日は見えなかった
Yesterday it rained, so the sun set behind the clouds.
Very much so.
そう じっとりと降り続く雨
The rain was drumming gracefully.
The darkness of dusk was closing in.
そして迫る夕闇
Oh, the impression that then clung onto her!
肌に絡みつく不快感と ノイズのような雨音
Oh, the delicate noise of the rain!
いい加減だな
You're overdoing it.
音色に誘われ 音楽室に入ると
As she entered the music room, the melody she had followed died abruptly.
途端に音は鳴り止んだ
The lid of the piano was open, but no pianist was to be seen.
ピアノの蓋は上がっているのにピアニストはいない
カーテンが閉めきられて部屋は暗い
The curtains were closed, and the room was dark.
そして彼女は見た
Then she saw her.
Let music  be heard
Her disheveled hair hung over her face.
長い乱れ髪を顔に垂らし 全身はぐったりとして力なく
Her body looked limp and powerless.
The girl's blazing eyes stared at her across the room from under half-closed eyelids.
目は爛々と血走った女生徒が 傍らから彼女をじっと見つめているのを
Indeed! In this very Kamiyama High,
そう この神山高校にはかつて
there was once a pianist, who on the eve of the national competition—
全国大会を前にして無念の事故死を遂げたピアノ部員が
Was there now?
いたのか
Dunno. There could well have been, but I don't know anything about it.
さあ いたかもしれないけど僕知らないね
だと思った
I thought so.
But I don't often see you staying so late after school.
それにしても意外だね 奉太郎が宿題を忘れて居残りなんて
Usually, you remember to do your homework.
I did do it!
書いたさ昨日
I just forgot to bring it with me.
持ってくるのを忘れたんだ
Thanks to that I have to write the same essay all over again while listening to you blabber on about nothing.
お陰でこうして 同じ作文を書きながら与太話を聞かされてる
I see.
なるほどね
By the way, they say there really is a ghost with disheveled hair somewhere in the school.
ちなみに 乱れ髪のお化けは本当にいたそうだよ
I heard Class A talking about it during lunch break.
今日の昼休み A組では話題になってたみたいだしね
Now all that matters is how the rumor will spread.
後はこの噂がどう広がっていくか これが重要なんだ
"The second of Kamiyama High's seven wonders!" Or something like that.
神山高校にもあった七不思議 その二ってね
I'm also interested to see how long it'll take for it to reach me in Class D.
差しあたっては僕のD組に到達するまで何日かかるかだ
Just a minute. Who did you hear that from? And where?
ちょっと待て 今の話 いつどこで 誰から聞いたんだ
Chitanda told me a little while ago, in the clubroom.
さっき部室で 千反田さんから
You said it could be the second wonder. So there's already a first?
七不思議その二ってことはその一もあるんだよな
What is it? Can you tell me?
聞かせてくれないか
So here's where you two were!
お二人ともここにいたんですか
I filled out the paperwork, Fukube.
書きました 福部さん
うん お疲れ様
Thank you.
ごめんね
Sorry. As a member of the Student Council, I've got to put you through some red tape as well.
総務委員会としてはこういう面倒な手続きもお願しないといけなくて
It's okay.
いいえ 私も部長を引き受けていますから
After all, I was the one who agreed to be club president.
折木さん
Oreki!
いいところに来た
You got here at just the right time.
Satoshi just told me about this weird rumor.
今里志から妙な噂を聞いたんだ
Oh, that! During lunch break—
ああ そのことなんです 昼休みに
秘密クラブの勧誘メモの話なんだが 知ってたのか
It's about the secret club. Did you know about it?
The secret club?
秘密クラブ
里志 話してやってくれよ
Satoshi, tell her please.
Sure.
じゃ お聞き願おうかな 秘密クラブの一席を
Listen closely. I'll tell you all about the secret club, and the controversy surrounding it.
Okay.
はい
I heard about it from the other council members.
総務委員会で聞いた話なんだ
The school has lots of clubs,
なにせ神山高校には部活が多い
so there are always lots of recruitment posters,
だから勧誘ポスターの数も当然多くなって
学校中の掲示板がポスターで埋め尽くされる
and the school's bulletin boards are usually filled with them.
総務員会は無免許のポスターやメモを見つけ次第
If the council finds unauthorized posters, we remove them.
剝しているんだ
However!
ところが
There's always one mysterious poster that doesn't belong to any club, but it shows up every single year.
毎年たった一枚 どこの部活のものかも分からない勧誘メモが出るらしい
去年はノートの切れ端しみたいな紙に 集合場所と日時が書いてあったそうだよ
Last year, it was just the time and place for a meeting, written on a scrap of paper.
どうやら総務委員会も把握していない秘密クラブがあって
There seems to be a secret club outside the authority of the council,
ひっそりと募集をかけているらしいんだ
covertly recruiting new members.
Diligence Determination
We don't know what they do or who they are, but they exist.
活動目的も部員も不明だけど
奴らは実在する
その名前とは
Their name is...
Their name is?
その名前とは
The Golden Web.
女郎蜘蛛の会
女郎蜘蛛
The Golden Web...
Last year Tanabe, president of the Student Council, tried to make contact with them after seeing their poster.
総務委員長の田辺先輩は去年回収したメモを頼りに女郎蜘蛛の会に接触しようとしたらしい
It didn't work out.
でもうまく行かなかった
結局名前だけのいたずらメモだと結論したそうだよ
They concluded that it was just a prank, given the name.
However...
ところが
However?
On the day of the graduation ceremony, one of the graduates told Tanabe:
卒業式の日 ある卒業生が田辺先輩に言ったんだ
僕が女郎蜘蛛の会の会長だった
"I was the president of the Golden Web.
Take good care of the next president as well...
次期会長にもよろしくしてやってくれ もし君がそいつを見つけ出せたらの話だが
if you can find him, that is."
I'm sure they're recruiting this year as well.
今年もきっとどこかに募集が出ているだろうね
Though, we haven't found any posters yet.
今のところ発見には至ってないけど
A single recruitment poster...
一枚だけのメモ
from the Golden Web.
女郎蜘蛛の会
I can't stop thinking about it!
私 気になります
Gotcha!
よし
I thought you'd say that.
そう言うと思ってた
That's why I said that you'd arrived at just the right time.
だからいいところに来たと言ったんだ
と言いますと
So?
Naturally, we're going to look for that poster.
もちろん探すんだよ そのメモを
Okay!
はい
There are thirty bulletin boards altogether.
掲示板は全部で三十カ所だね
That's a lot... Are we going to check them all?
そんなに 全部探しますか
まさか
No way.
It'd be faster if we worked out the most likely place beforehand.
一番ありそうなのはどこか考えたほうが速い
なるほど
I see.
Where do you think it'd be?
どういう条件の場所だと思う
If I were them, I'd put it in some out-of-the-way place where it wasn't too noticeable.
もし私だったら
やっぱりできるだけ目立たない 校舎の隅の掲示板に張ると思います
それは違うな
You're missing the point.
Really?
違いますか
もし勧誘メモが張られているとするなら
If there really is a poster, then it'll be on the bulletin board in front of the main entrance.
それは 一階昇降口の掲示板だ
ええ 一番目立つ所じゃないですか
But that's the most conspicuous place it could be!
まあまあ 千反田さん
Don't worry,
Houtarou's probably on to something.
奉太郎には何か考えがあるらしいよ
Looking at all these posters again, this school never fails to impress me.
やあ 改めてみるとやっぱりすごいね 神山高校
本当ですね
Really...
水墨画部 漫画研究会 囲碁部 バスケ部  陸上部
India Ink Club, Manga Lab, Track & Field and Basketball teams...
There is no end to them!
掲示板の本体が見えません
What's wrong, Oreki?
折木さん どうしたんですか
いや 溢れ出る活力に当てられて
I was just overwhelmed by the combined enthusiasm of everyone who drew these posters...
It's entirely beyond the understanding of a low-energy person like you, isn't it?
省エネの奉太郎には理解不能な世界だろうね
それにここは新入生がまず見る掲示板だ つまり激戦区だよ
And this is the bulletin board that the first-year students see as soon as they arrive.
This is a real battlefield.
激戦区 ああ なるほど
A battlefield?
Of course! With this many posters, the unauthorized ones would just blend in!
これだけたくさん張ってあれば 無許可な掲示物も目立ちませんね
That's also true.
それもある
それも 別の理由があるんですか
Also?
Is there something else?
Kind of.
まあな
Let's take a look at the board to begin with.
とにかく探してみよう
Okay.
はい
The Global Theater, the Debate Circle...
グローバル アクト部 ディベート部 百人一首部なんてのもあるんですね
We even have a 100 Poets Club!
Oh, the Fortunetelling Lab!
占い研究会 私の友達がここに入ったんです
My friend joined that!
Composers' Club, Table Tennis, Art Club...
筝曲部 卓球部 美術部
女郎蜘蛛の会のメモはないようですね
I don't see the Golden Web's poster anywhere...
どうかな 見ただけで分かるようになっているかどうかはちょっと分からないよね
I wonder...
We shouldn't expect to recognize it immediately.
あっ どういうことですか
What do you mean?
総務員の目を盗むには 何か工夫があるかもしれないなと思ってね
They probably have some trick to avoid being noticed by the council.
Trick?
工夫ですか
But if it's here, I'm sure we'll find it sooner or later.
ま あるならいずれ見つかるよ
あったぞ
It's here.
The Golden Web
Two members needed
It's really here.
ありましたね もっと人気のない場所に隠すかと思ったのに
I thought it'd be in a more secluded place.
それは一年生の発想だ
That's how a first-year student would think.
不慣れなやつほど気をてらう
The more inexperienced you are, the more you want to show off.
But if you were clever enough to run a secret club, you'd try to outwit people in a more dignified way.
気の利いた秘密クラブなら堂々と裏を書いてくると睨んだんだ
That's true.
確かに
But it's weird...
でも不思議です そう言われるとあるのが当然という気がして
When you put it that way, it's pretty obvious.
I guess I'm not surprised.
なぜか驚きがありません
Anyway, this is an unauthorized poster.
総務委員会許可印なし 仕事するね
In the end, I gotta do my job.
Well then,
さて 俺は作文を職員室に出してそのまま帰るよ
I'm going to turn in my essay at the staff room then go home.
Yeah,
そうだね 僕も帰ろうかな
I think I'll head home too.
Okay.
分かりました ではここでさようならですね
Then let's say goodbye here for today.
不慣れな人ほど気をてらう 覚えておきますね
The more inexperienced you are, the more you want to show off.
I'll remember that.
不思議を持って不思議を制すの形 お見事だったよ
I guess the best way to tame a mystery is with another mystery.
Well done.
世話んなったな 何だかあいつが来そうな予感がしたんだ
Thanks for your help.
I just knew she'd show up.
So that's why you made that note and pinned it to the board.
それであんなメモや画鋲を用意したと
Well, it worked out pretty well in the end.
まあ 結果どんぴしゃだったね
But why would you go so far as to turn a simple mystery into something so grand?
でも 奉太郎
あそこまで手の込んだ真似をして ピアノの謎から話を逸らせたかったのはなぜだい
It's not because she's no match for you in that regard, right?
まさかそっちには歯がたたないから なんて言わないよね
音楽室は遠いからな
Because the music room was too far away.
それだけ
That's it?
That's it.
それだけだ
まっすぐ昇降口まで行ってそばの職員室に作文を出して
I just wanted to go past the main entrance, hand in my essay at the staff room and go straight home.
そのまま帰りたかった
I see. I get it.
なるほど 分かった
You're you, after all.
奉太郎だよ やっぱり
I can't stop thinking about it!
私 気になります
"What I have to do, I do quickly."
やらなければやらないことなら手短にだ
Houtarou, that won't do.
奉太郎 それはよくないね
You should recite your motto with your head held high.
もっとお披露をするなら堂々と胸を張って言うべきだ
今の奉太郎は単に言い訳をしたようにしか聞こえない
The way you said it just then sounded like a mere excuse.
The best way to tame a mystery is with another mystery.
不思議を不思議で迎え撃つ うん 僕好みだ
I like that.
It's a good breaking ball.
いい変化球だよ
だけどね 奉太郎 それは奉太郎好みじゃないよ
But you know, Houtarou,
that's not the way you do things.
When Chitanda showed up,
千反田さんが来た時 どうして単に知らんと言わなかったんだい
why didn't you just tell her that you didn't know anything about it?
That was your first mistake.
そこが今日の奉太郎の根本的な間違いだよ
実際奉太郎はずっとそうしてきたじゃないか
You've always been able to just turn people down until now.
I guess.
そうかもな
"The more inexperienced you are, the more you want to show off."
不慣れな奴ほど気をてらう
今日の奉太郎がまさしくそれだよ
That fits you perfectly today.
You're not used to being around her at all,
千反田さんがいるっていう状況に まだ全然慣れてない
だからあんな回りくどいことをするのさ
and that's why you sorted things out in such a roundabout way.
You may have just wanted to reject her,
奉太郎さんは今日千反田さんを拒絶したつもりかもしれない
but—
でもね
拒絶したかったわけじゃない
I wanted to do no such thing.
Of course, I know.
もちろんそうさ
You just wanted to hold on to the status quo.
あれは現状に対するただの保留だね
保留
Hold on?
I see. So I'm just holding on...
そうか 保留か
What do you think about mystery of the music room, by the way?
ところで 音楽室の件はどういうことだったんと思う
ああ そのお化けとやらは髪が乱れて 目が血走ってたんだろ
Her hair was messy and her eyes were half closed,
寝起きのように
as if she just woke up, right?
あっ そうか
I see.
ピアノ部員は眠かったから寝ていた
The pianist was sleepy, so she took a nap.
校門が締まる6時前に目が覚めるように
She put on the Moonlight Sonata to play so that she would wake up before the school closed at six.
CDプレーヤーに月光を入れてタイマーをセットしていた
I guess that's about it.
そんなことだろう
I see. I suppose that explains it.
なるほどね 確かに言えば分かる
In that case, the CD player would probably still be set up.
プレーヤーに設定が残っているだろうし
But the music room is too far away.
音楽室は遠いからな
Got it.
分かったって ただね 奉太郎
But, you know,
I get the feeling that going there would've cost you less energy in the long run.
音楽室まで行ってたほうが 行く行くは省エネにつながったような気がするんだ
You might be all right today,
今日の屈託は意外と高くつくかもしれない
but it could cost you more in the future.
Houtarou!
奉太郎 今日のこと 僕は貸しにする気はないよ
Don't worry about owing me anything for today!
Bye!
じゃ
Holding on, huh?
保留 か
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Next time: Activities of the esteemed Classics Club
Activities of the esteemed Classics Club
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
まどろみの約束
芽生えてた温もり　暖かくて戸惑う
こんな気持ちをまだ　あなたは分からないよ
そんな視線には意味なんて　別にないはず
だって友達にしてるのと同じ
明け方に消えてく　小さな願星
夜の間だけの魔法を…
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
まどろみの約束
次回 名誉ある古典部の活動